Organic chemists make molecules,
جعلت الكيمياء العضوية الجزيئات،
very complicated molecules,
معقدًة للغاية،
by chopping up a big molecule into small molecules
وذلك بواسطة تقسيم الجزيء الكبير إلى جزيئات صغيرة
and reverse engineering.
والهندسة العكسية.
And as a chemist,
و ككيميائي،
one of the things I wanted to ask my research group a couple of years ago is,
فإن إحدى الأمور التي أردت أن أسأل عنها مجموعتي البحثية قبل عدة سنين هي،
could we make a really cool universal chemistry set?
هل يمكننا تقديم مجموعة كيمياء عالمية رائعة حقا؟
In essence, could we "app" chemistry?
أو في جوهرها، هل يمكننا "تطبيق" الكيمياء؟
Now what would this mean, and how would we do it?
الآن ماذا يعني ذلك، وكيف سنفعل ذلك؟
Well to start to do this,
حسنا للبدء في القيام بذلك،
we took a 3D printer
أخذنا طابعة ثلاثية الأبعاد
and we started to print our beakers and our test tubes on one side
وبدأنا بطباعة الأكواب و أنابيب الإختبار لدنيا على جانب واحد
and then print the molecule at the same time on the other side
ومن ثم طباعة الجزيء في الوقت نفسه على الجانب الآخر،
and combine them together in what we call reactionware.
والجمع بينهما معا في ما نسميه ال "Reactionware".
And so by printing the vessel and doing the chemistry at the same time,
وبذلك ومن خلال طباعة الوعاء والقيام بالكيمياء في الوقت نفسه،
we may start to access this universal toolkit of chemistry.
فإنه يمكنننا أن نبدأ في الولوج إلى مجموعة أدوات عالمية للكيمياء.
Now what could this mean?
الآن ماذا يمكن أن يعني ذلك؟
Well if we can embed biological and chemical networks like a search engine,
حسنا لو تمكنا من تضمين الشبكات البيولوجية والكيميائية مثل محرك بحث،
so if you have a cell that's ill that you need to cure
بحيث انه إذا كانت لديك خلية مريضة تحتاج إلى علاج
or bacteria that you want to kill,
أو بكتيريا تريد قتلها،
if you have this embedded in your device
و كان لديك هذا المحرك مضمنًا في جهازك الخاص
at the same time, and you do the chemistry,
وتقوم بالكيمياء، في الوقت ذاته
you may be able to make drugs in a new way.
فقد تكون قادرًا على صنع العقاقير بطريقة جديدة.
So how are we doing this in the lab?
كيف سنقوم بذلك في المختبر؟
Well it requires software, it requires hardware
حسنًا إن الأمر يتطلب برمجيات ومعدات
and it requires chemical inks.
ويتطلب أحباراً كيميائيةً ايضًا.
And so the really cool bit is,
ولذا فإن الجزء المثيرهو،
the idea is that we want to have a universal set of inks
الفكرة في أننا نريد أن نحصل على مجموعة من الأحبار العالمية
that we put out with the printer,
التي سوف تتوائم مع الطابعة،
and you download the blueprint, the organic chemistry for that molecule
ويمكنك تحميل مخطط الكيمياء العضوية لهذا الجزيء
and you make it in the device.
وصنعه في الجهاز.
And so you can make your molecule in the printer using this software.
وهكذا يمكنك صنع جزيئك في الطابعة باستخدام هذه البرمجية.
So what could this mean?
حسنًا ماذا يمكن أن يعني هذا؟
Well, ultimately, it could mean that you could print your own medicine.
حسنا، في نهاية المطاف، يمكن أن يعني أنه يمكنك طباعة دوائك الخاص بك.
And this is what we're doing in the lab at the moment.
وهذا ما نقوم به في المختبر في الوقت الحالي.
But to take baby steps to get there,
ولكن لنبدأ خطواتنا الاولى للوصول إلى ذلك،
first of all we want to look at drug design and production,
فإنه يجب علينا أولاً وقبل كل شيء أن ننظر في علوم تصميم الأدوية والإنتاج،
or drug discovery and manufacturing.
أو اكتشاف الأدوية والتصنيع.
Because if we can manufacture it after we've discovered it,
لأنه إذا تمكننا من تصنيعه بعد اكتشافنا له،
we could deploy it anywhere.
فسنتمكن من نشره في أي مكان.
You don't need to go to the chemist anymore.
لن تحتاج إلى الذهاب إلى الصيدلي بعد الآن.
We can print drugs at point of need.
فنحن سنتمكن من طباعة العقاقير لحظة حاجتنا لها.
We can download new diagnostics.
يمكننا تحميل تشاخيص جديدة.
Say a new super bug has emerged.
لنفترض أن هناك جرثومة خطيرة قد ظهرت .
You put it in your search engine,
يمكنك وضعها في محرك البحث الخاص بك،
and you create the drug to treat the threat.
ويمكنك إنشاء العقاقير والتعامل مع التهديد.
So this allows you on-the-fly molecular assembly.
لذا فإن هذا سوف يسمح لك بتجميع الجزئ في لمح البصر.
But perhaps for me the core bit going into the future
ولكن ربما بالنسبة لي فإن جوهر الأمر سيكون في المستقبل
is this idea of taking your own stem cells,
هل تعتقد أن فكرة أخذ خلاياك الجذعية،
with your genes and your environment,
مع جيناتك وبيئك،
and you print your own personal medicine.
وطباعة دوائك الشخصي .
And if that doesn't seem fanciful enough,
تبدو خيالية؟ وإذا كانت لا تبدو كذلك بما فيه الكفاية،
where do you think we're going to go?
فأين تعتقد أننا بصدد الذهاب؟
Well, you're going to have your own personal matter fabricator.
حسنا، سوف يكون لك مُصَنِّعٌ خاصٌ لأمورك الشخصية.
Beam me up, Scotty.
أنيروا دربي، سكوتي.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)